<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-04-28T22:09:42+00:00</updated><id>https://kryptokommun.ist/feed.xml</id><title type="html">kryptokommunist’s personal blog</title><subtitle>Making machines help humans to be more human instead of making humans more like machines.</subtitle><author><name>Marcus Ding</name></author><entry><title type="html">My First Five-Day Silent Retreat: Jhanas &amp;amp; Alexander Technique</title><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/meditation/jhanas/therapy/english/2023/04/20/my-first-five-day-silent-retreat-jhanas-and-alexander-technique.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My First Five-Day Silent Retreat: Jhanas &amp; Alexander Technique" /><published>2023-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kryptokommun.ist/meditation/jhanas/therapy/english/2023/04/20/my-first-five-day-silent-retreat-jhanas-and-alexander-technique</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kryptokommun.ist/meditation/jhanas/therapy/english/2023/04/20/my-first-five-day-silent-retreat-jhanas-and-alexander-technique.html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, I went on my first silent retreat at &lt;a href=&quot;https://gaiahouse.co.uk&quot;&gt;Gaia House&lt;/a&gt; in Britain. I was drawn to the place by the charm and resonance of Rob Burbea’s teachings, which I listened to on &lt;a href=&quot;https://dharmaseed.org&quot;&gt;dharmaseed.org&lt;/a&gt;. He was a resident teacher at Gaia House, and the retreat I attended was led by Catherine McGee and Yahel Avigur, both of whom were strongly influenced by his teachings. The retreat was a challenging but still surprisingly effortless and very rewarding experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the retreat, I went to London, which was quite a stark contrast to the quiet and peaceful scenery of the rural landscape around the retreat center oozing stillness and peacefulness. But even though it was harder to notice, I could still access the stillness within. It’s always there when I am sensitive enough to look for it. I also noticed colors more intensely and saw the positive and beautiful everywhere, all after five days of maybe six hours of daily meditation in a mix of walking and sitting meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gaiahouse1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gaiahouse2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gaiahouse3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; The library and the entire place is truly beautiful and encourages you to become more present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure now that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Technique&quot;&gt;Alexander Technique&lt;/a&gt; is basically a form of social body awareness meditation. You can get to the same place without a teacher and just by returning awareness to the whole body over and over. It’s also bringing students to expanded awareness and ultimately &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nondualism&quot;&gt;nondual awareness&lt;/a&gt;. Over the five days, I noticed my awareness expanding outside but also within my body. At some point, I could feel my hips during walking and generally my whole body. That then automatically improved my posture because my body would automatically untense as soon as awareness was in the tensed area. Also, the feeling after the retreat coming back to the city was similar to receiving Alexander Technique sessions and then walking through Berlin. Awareness is expanded, and I just look everywhere more curiously. There is joy in more small things, the neon light in front of the restaurant, the palm trees. The small becomes big and magical. So there’s more joy in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main takeaway was that I realized I could still meditate with less effort. Just holding the intention of whatever the goal of the meditation is lightly is enough. Willpower, at the point I am at, is of no more value. And I can notice the effort level in my breath. The more effort I put into meditation (or anything else, for that matter), the more turbulent my breath feels. When there is no effort, the breath feels like a laminar flow without any resistance and is barely audible. I realized that in the big meditation hall, when my breath was significantly more audible, that I was still efforting way more than needed, even when breathing out. But breathing out requires no effort. Doing nothing, the exhale just happens. With this more light way of meditating, I am more sensitive, and I can still work with upcoming dullness or boredom. Instead of using effort, I use the gentle but firm intention of returning to my goal of meditation and addressing whatever concern with acceptance and love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing I loved about the retreat was Catherine McGee’s charisma in person, which really stood out. She radiated a loving softness with a very confident and strong core. Something I have not seen in a person I met in person before. Some meditation teachers come off as loving but maybe somehow in an unbalanced soft way. She embodied what she spoke of and also explicitly pointed out some things I was missing in many meditation instructions. For example, her approach is very body-centered. So starting off with a shake session and just patting down your own body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another new idea I got from the retreat was in a talk by Catherine McGee, who explained how emptiness can help you be sensitive without becoming overwhelmed. I always struggled with meditation making me overly sensitive and wondered how I could cope with it in the real world. McGee pointed out that emptiness is not a goal in itself but rather a tool that can help you navigate the world while being sensitive.
Another new idea I got from the retreat was in a talk by Catherine McGee, who explained how emptiness can help you be sensitive without becoming overwhelmed. I always struggled with meditation making me overly sensitive and wondered how I could cope with it in the real world. McGee pointed out that emptiness is not a goal in itself but rather a tool that can help you navigate the world while being sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another valuable insight McGee shared was that having attention in your belly can help you stay grounded. This point resonated with me and helped me to cultivate more groundedness in my daily life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the retreat, I was able to access &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0K5ypXyF3dY&quot;&gt;Jhana&lt;/a&gt; one and two, which was a significant accomplishment for me. I could access them two years ago and then lost the ability to access them. Basically I put in a lot of effort over two years to learn that I need to stop putting in so much effort if I want to access them. I found that by holding the intention of accessing Jhana gently and patiently, I could enter these states more easily. What I found most powerful was imagining a loving other in the second Jhana. It felt like having a real person hold space for my parts and difficult emotions. The after-effects were remarkable, with more equanimity and joy throughout the day. In the Jhanas, attention and awareness are like train tracks that won’t budge, which helped me bring awareness to body parts that needed healing. I want to use the Jhanas to do Internal Family Systems healing work on myself rather than starting insight practice. That seems healthier to me, first strengthen psychological health before I start deconstructing my ways of looking and perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also attended an Alexander Technique workshop after the retreat, which helped me realize that I could put even less effort into accessing the Jhanas after noticing how it is easier to catch a ball if I just don’t use any effort and let my body do it perfectly. During the Alexander Technique class, I learned how attention and awareness work in social group dynamics and how they relate to power and status. When people see someone as high status, they give them attention, and that person then directs others’ attention and awareness. With meditation and Alexander Technique, the goal is to direct awareness and attention mostly to oneself, which gives you permission to go wherever you want. So it’s understandable why people want to have a career and high status, it feels more fun to be in expanded awareness in social settings. But what many people don’t know is with meditation or Alexander Technique you get the same feeling, but without having to rely on external factors to give you permission. What an amazing pitch for meditation that is huh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Alexander Technique class, when the teacher opened the student’s awareness, I could feel the student seeming to command the room as an equal to the teacher. However, a pitfall of Alexander Technique is that this experience of expanded awareness may be tied to permission from the teacher more easily than with meditation. With meditation practice, the teacher is far removed, so you realize that you are giving yourself permission to expand your awareness. But a good Alexander Technique teacher should be aware of this and make sure you credit yourself for expanding your awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, attending a silent retreat and learning about Jhanas and Alexander Technique was a life-changing experience for me. I’m grateful for the insights and tools I gained, and I hope to continue integrating them into my daily life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marcus Ding</name></author><category term="[&quot;meditation&quot;, &quot;jhanas&quot;, &quot;therapy&quot;, &quot;English&quot;]" /><category term="meditation" /><category term="jhanas" /><category term="therapy" /><summary type="html">Last week, I went on my first silent retreat at Gaia House in Britain. I was drawn to the place by the charm and resonance of Rob Burbea’s teachings, which I listened to on dharmaseed.org. He was a resident teacher at Gaia House, and the retreat I attended was led by Catherine McGee and Yahel Avigur, both of whom were strongly influenced by his teachings. The retreat was a challenging but still surprisingly effortless and very rewarding experience. At the end of the retreat, I went to London, which was quite a stark contrast to the quiet and peaceful scenery of the rural landscape around the retreat center oozing stillness and peacefulness. But even though it was harder to notice, I could still access the stillness within. It’s always there when I am sensitive enough to look for it. I also noticed colors more intensely and saw the positive and beautiful everywhere, all after five days of maybe six hours of daily meditation in a mix of walking and sitting meditation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to notice a great therapist</title><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/trauma/therapy/english/2023/01/27/how-to-notice-a-great-therapist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to notice a great therapist" /><published>2023-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kryptokommun.ist/trauma/therapy/english/2023/01/27/how-to-notice-a-great-therapist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kryptokommun.ist/trauma/therapy/english/2023/01/27/how-to-notice-a-great-therapist.html">&lt;p&gt;You have decided that you want to get serious about loving all of you and want to start working with a therapist or changing from one you are not quite sure about. I commend you on your courage, deciding to look inwards, even if parts of you might be worried about what lurks in your subconscious. Looking inside and being really curious about yourself is an revolutionary act in todays world. And unlike a view of being curious and involved with yourself as narcissistic, it’s very different. Trying to control how you and others see yourself is narcissistic, based on deep fears. Being curious and open to see who you really are from a place of love is healing and will benefit not only yourself but everyone around you. Your relationship to the parts of yourself is how you relate to everyone else. No one can be more intimate and loving towards you than yourself. That is the threshold of how much you can let in from others. And that threshold can be infinitely larger than you imagine right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June of 2022, during a trip to the US, I worked with a therapist that completely changed my view of how much positive change is possible with a great therapist. Working with this therapist was as psychoactive as the psychedelic experiences I had, only that these changes in how I perceived me and the world stayed permanently. This therapist would just sit in front of me and ask me to scan my body. On the first day, my awareness of my body was strong as never before. I could notice when I would dissociate and the room would feel bigger. 
I would notice when a fear in me arose that projected that the therapist might hit me. All that was a level of awareness I had never had access to before. I noticed how I used humor to distract from fear. I cried in session three. After every appointment, I felt hopeful and joyful as never before. My mind got quiet, and I could enjoy just sitting in the park and watching the birds. Something I would have never done before. All of this within a week of three hours of daily therapy. Even when you discount that, before, I did half a year of weekly behavior therapy and never experienced such fundamental shifts in well-being. I never left the appointments feeling joy and hope. That new therapy experience made me realize that before, I was afraid of the therapy appointments because the therapist was afraid of my emotions. I only cried once with the previous therapist within half a year because she subconsciously communicated that she couldn’t hold my sadness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, with the therapist from the US, I noticed that opening up so many things so quickly was also destabilizing because when I moved back to Berlin, I now needed to continue without her presence. That was also due to losing trust because she had a weak spot that she could not address when I raised it. So what makes a great therapist? Here is my answer in the hope that it may inspire you to find yours. Overall it seems that the therapist can only raise you to their own level of awareness, emotional resiliency, and healing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, what is the goal of therapy? It’s learning to become aware of parts of your mind that you are hiding from yourself. It’s to learn to love the parts of yourself that you disown. It’s learning to become more embodied or embodied at all. It’s learning to feel safe in your body. It’s learning to notice how feeling relates to body sensations. It’s learning to let the emotions move through you rather than fully identifying with them. It’s learning to love all of your emotional experiences, especially the difficult ones. It’s learning to have boundaries. It’s understanding who you are and stopping wanting to change. It’s learning to know that you are already perfect. It’s learning that whatever you dislike about yourself is a natural, human reaction to your life experience. First I thought that crying often is a sign of a good therapist, but then some people, like me, have parts blocking crying at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;A simple heuristic for how good the therapist is: How often do you notice shifts in how you relate to yourself and others after your sessions? And how much do you feel like you are responsible for your progress?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of those things can show up in very obvious or subtle ways. If you have a history of trauma, your first instinct is likely to doubt yourself. Actually, from my experience, your body will likely know pretty well what’s going on. If you avoid going to your appointments, e.g., by being late, and you don’t feel better afterward or, even worse, your body is telling you something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what will a great therapist do to support you in that?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;never judges you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;always on your side&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they can sit with your sadness, and you can cry around them. But, if you never cry, you are most likely picking up on them, not being okay with your sadness.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they want to work with you long-term&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they do not worry about you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are open to your feedback, and your suggestions (let’s walk outside, I want to go outside for a break)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are stable in their emotions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they can hold your gaze for a long time without hardness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are gentle and know that slower is faster with trauma&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is aware of transference and will work with it, making you feel it’s safe to discuss how you feel towards them. E.g., you project your mother onto your therapist and feel like she might be disappointed about something you said, but you feel safe to tell your therapist, and they don’t feel threatened in their identity but rather work with that.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they mainly help you to notice things in your body and mind&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they point you to yourself a lot; they are humble and curious. So your progress will feel like it’s all your work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they create a relationship where you feel like an equal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they ooze a nonjudgemental ness and openness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they will teach you techniques to regulate your nervous system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they know about dissociation and can notice when you dissociate and then do exercises with you to regulate your nervous system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they don’t want you to change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are more curious about you than you are yourself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you are chronically late, see that as a sign that parts of you are afraid of the therapy appointment and address that directly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they know and have experience with meditation practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they will not just talk with you; they will use hypnosis, exercises, embodiment, and pauses to allow you to get out of your head into your body and emotions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they will let you have your emotions and not interfere with that&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they will do boundary work with you; they will train you to say no and feel your inner boundaries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are aware of how deep the impact of trauma goes, they will be open to you asking to leave the room, going for a walk outside, asking for shaking your body alone in the room, etc., to feel safe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if they are insanely great, they will even suggest those things above to you when they notice you are triggered and dissociating&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they learn from you and want to learn from you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are creative and think for themselves; they don’t follow strict rules but rather experiment with what works&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;their main agenda is for you to become more you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What will a well-intentioned but not great therapist do to keep you stuck?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;think they know what you need better than yourself, and you might start believing them at some point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can’t deal with big emotions; they will subtly signal that they are uncomfortable with what you share or you are being emotional. E.g., crossing their arms, slightly tensing their eyes when you become emotional or talk about a problematic experience. You might even feel you are a burden or manipulative because you subconsciously sense that they are afraid of your emotions (it’s called countertransference).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they create a relationship where you feel they have authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they will worry about you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they want you to change and want your approval&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;see drug use as a problem without being curious about the underlying pain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they will only talk about emotions to avoid emotions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they will try to make you feel better&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they think that just experiencing the pain is healing when actually the amount of pain felt must be met with an equal amount of love and patience. Anything else is just reexperiencing trauma.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strictly follow the rules and guidelines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;promises you quick solutions and fixes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they want you to become like someone they imagine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May your heart be filled with love for all your parts, friend. May you have a safe journey inside and through this mystical adventure of life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marcus Ding</name></author><category term="[&quot;trauma&quot;, &quot;therapy&quot;, &quot;English&quot;]" /><category term="trauma" /><category term="therapy" /><summary type="html">You have decided that you want to get serious about loving all of you and want to start working with a therapist or changing from one you are not quite sure about. I commend you on your courage, deciding to look inwards, even if parts of you might be worried about what lurks in your subconscious. Looking inside and being really curious about yourself is an revolutionary act in todays world. And unlike a view of being curious and involved with yourself as narcissistic, it’s very different. Trying to control how you and others see yourself is narcissistic, based on deep fears. Being curious and open to see who you really are from a place of love is healing and will benefit not only yourself but everyone around you. Your relationship to the parts of yourself is how you relate to everyone else. No one can be more intimate and loving towards you than yourself. That is the threshold of how much you can let in from others. And that threshold can be infinitely larger than you imagine right now. In June of 2022, during a trip to the US, I worked with a therapist that completely changed my view of how much positive change is possible with a great therapist. Working with this therapist was as psychoactive as the psychedelic experiences I had, only that these changes in how I perceived me and the world stayed permanently. This therapist would just sit in front of me and ask me to scan my body. On the first day, my awareness of my body was strong as never before. I could notice when I would dissociate and the room would feel bigger. I would notice when a fear in me arose that projected that the therapist might hit me. All that was a level of awareness I had never had access to before. I noticed how I used humor to distract from fear. I cried in session three. After every appointment, I felt hopeful and joyful as never before. My mind got quiet, and I could enjoy just sitting in the park and watching the birds. Something I would have never done before. All of this within a week of three hours of daily therapy. Even when you discount that, before, I did half a year of weekly behavior therapy and never experienced such fundamental shifts in well-being. I never left the appointments feeling joy and hope. That new therapy experience made me realize that before, I was afraid of the therapy appointments because the therapist was afraid of my emotions. I only cried once with the previous therapist within half a year because she subconsciously communicated that she couldn’t hold my sadness. On the other hand, with the therapist from the US, I noticed that opening up so many things so quickly was also destabilizing because when I moved back to Berlin, I now needed to continue without her presence. That was also due to losing trust because she had a weak spot that she could not address when I raised it. So what makes a great therapist? Here is my answer in the hope that it may inspire you to find yours. Overall it seems that the therapist can only raise you to their own level of awareness, emotional resiliency, and healing: First, what is the goal of therapy? It’s learning to become aware of parts of your mind that you are hiding from yourself. It’s to learn to love the parts of yourself that you disown. It’s learning to become more embodied or embodied at all. It’s learning to feel safe in your body. It’s learning to notice how feeling relates to body sensations. It’s learning to let the emotions move through you rather than fully identifying with them. It’s learning to love all of your emotional experiences, especially the difficult ones. It’s learning to have boundaries. It’s understanding who you are and stopping wanting to change. It’s learning to know that you are already perfect. It’s learning that whatever you dislike about yourself is a natural, human reaction to your life experience. First I thought that crying often is a sign of a good therapist, but then some people, like me, have parts blocking crying at times. A simple heuristic for how good the therapist is: How often do you notice shifts in how you relate to yourself and others after your sessions? And how much do you feel like you are responsible for your progress?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fantastic Planet – A 1973 movie revealing hidden truths about the human mind and human condition</title><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/trauma/english/2022/11/01/fantastic-planet.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fantastic Planet – A 1973 movie revealing hidden truths about the human mind and human condition" /><published>2022-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kryptokommun.ist/trauma/english/2022/11/01/fantastic-planet</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kryptokommun.ist/trauma/english/2022/11/01/fantastic-planet.html">&lt;p&gt;A friend recommended me the old sci-fi classic &lt;em&gt;Fantastic Planet&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-7LuNSHlPco&quot;&gt;link to the whole movie&lt;/a&gt;). This movie and its reception hold the key to understanding a lot of human behavior and functioning around dissociation, trauma, and human sexuality. It’s a great example of how mindful awareness and investigation help to understand something that possibly millions of humans who watched the movie did not fully piece together. I invite you to watch the film before reading the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please note: This text explores sexual abuse.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick summary of the movie is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Nothing else has ever looked or felt like director René Laloux s animated marvel Fantastic Planet, a politically minded and visually inventive work of science fiction. The film is set on a distant planet called Ygam, where enslaved humans (Oms) are the playthings of giant blue natives (Draags). After Terr, kept as a pet since infancy, escapes from his gigantic child captor, he is swept up by a band of radical fellow Oms who resist the Draags oppression and violence. With its eerie, coolly surreal cutout animation by Roland Topor; brilliant psychedelic jazz score by Alain Goraguer; and wondrous creatures and landscapes, this Cannes-awarded 1973 counterculture classic is a perennially compelling statement against conformity and violence.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s dive into what it depicts and the meaning behind it. In the beginning, it introduces us to the blue giants that are the masters of the little human that is still a baby at this point in the plot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-7LuNSHlPco?clip=UgkxrF89rMfSpZ3cy93hNBsv8uWE2h6eSQ-G&amp;amp;clipt=EKrhGhjKgB4&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of the rest of the movie, this meditation refers to having sex while being dissociated. The eyes are turning red and the bubble floating above the blue aliens is a great visualization of dissociation, of disconnecting from the body. In the next scene, the relatively little human is encountering something in his host family:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zrJMgm6dBHA&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This key scene of the movie depicts sexual child abuse in a very detached and ingeniously subtle form. I know this might seem like a far-fetched claim. First of all, there are some details later in the movie that makes this interpretation obvious, and as well if you closely pay attention to what is happening, you can see this. The trick is not to interpret the scene literally and start to see and be aware of the meaning behind what is directly happening. You have to loosen your awareness and connect with the body to see this. Let’s take it slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fantastic-planet-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; The human child shows up at the beginning of this movie scene. The background seems alien, but it does not take much fantasy to see that these shapes resemble penises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fantastic-planet-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The child then sees a group of male aliens, and they start to close their eyes, dissociate, and disconnect. A black tentacle makes contact with their bodies, and the music implies pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fantastic-planet-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The group of male aliens lose their boundaries, and their bodies merge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fantastic-planet-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The small child is shocked, almost ashamed to have witnessed this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zrJMgm6dBHA?clip=UgkxifcIE2rbUgYZ1-aoyU57FX4rcf-id5is&amp;amp;clipt=EI-KBRjX_gY&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the men are caught, they just stop their act suddenly and pretend that nothing happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fantastic-planet-6.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The small child runs under a rain cloud. That represents fear and also grief; the rain is a detached depiction of tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fantastic-planet-7.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Notice how the child at the end of that rain scene, after running away in desperation smiles. It just puts on a good face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The child character says the telling words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
A drag week was equivalent to one of my years. I was just a live plaything who sometimes dared to rebel. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you read the reviews, discussions, and interpretations of the movie, it is astonishing how some people pick up on the movie being about how we should not hurt animals or how totalitarian regimes are evil. No one seems to see the most obvious here. It’s a story about how children growing up in abusive homes are powerless and at the mercy of their parents. With abusive parents, in the worst case, sexually abusive parents, their children are prisoners of giant aliens that they need to please, and they try to rebel, but their power is almost none compared to their parents. This movie is about how vulnerable children are. Something that not many that reviewed the movie seemed to have picked up on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next scene is one where my hunch about this being about child sexual abuse got very certain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-7LuNSHlPco?clip=UgkxZEPvXWcE3Oy_P0ritkFNJpnMrJbb6x3w&amp;amp;clipt=ENChXRiw9mA&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you remember the adult aliens’ dissociation meditation? Well, now here the movie explains that it was time for the children to be initiated to this as well. Now, what is sexual here? Again it’s so subtlely depicted that you need to loosen your awareness and become curious about the plants. In the movie reviews, many viewers mention that they found the bizarre plants particularly interesting. Well, if you look at them closely in this clip of the child meditation, you can make a stunning observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fantastic-planet-8.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Notice what these plants might point to in a sexual context. Without viewing these scenes through that way of looking, it's easy to miss this. The entire movie has a sexual undertone to activate this consciously and subconsciously. But let's put some more attention in here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fantastic-planet-9.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Maybe you did see it. These plants are pointing to anal and vaginal penetration. Together with the floating children, this scene also seems to be depicting sexual child abuse. The movie makes the allusions in such a distanced and relatively subtle way that I feel it's unclear if the movie makers were themselves fully aware of what they were writing and drawing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this and some more background story, the now adolescent human manages to escape his prison and flees. Not without encountering yet another pointer to the sexual undercurrent of this movie. I think no explanation is needed for this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-7LuNSHlPco?clip=Ugkxo20SXqDo2w4QI4hD9Y8MPlu7EIIllrRU&amp;amp;clipt=EMzhZBjLzGU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After fleeing, our adolescent main protagonist encounters a group of undomesticated wild humans that live in a park. There he observes their mating ritual. Symbolically it begins with them receiving some magical stones that make them glow. Also, they receive that glow while they walk over the dead skull of one of the blue aliens. This one is not entirely obvious, but it seems to me that healing of sexuality is depicted here. The humans in this sequence overcome their childhood abuse by symbolically climbing over the dead abuser and then engaging in adult, consensual sexuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-7LuNSHlPco?clip=Ugkx_B5H51K1v6zcNWawEklSkbe_8bwVR2RQ&amp;amp;clipt=ENGXfRix7IAB&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the movie’s end, the meaning of the meditation is revealed to be sexuality, and intercourse. The humans discover this, allowing them to force the blue aliens to give them their own planet and live without hate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-7LuNSHlPco?clip=UgkxDkUDF3k98Vp3ty_2Vvq_4Hp7wrdYhr8D&amp;amp;clipt=EIbG7QEY5prxAQ&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The movie has many other layers of meaning, but I focused on childhood sexual abuse because this side of the movie is not mentioned by any review or comment. So given the above, I hope to have shown that this movie is an ingeniously subtle and covert depiction of child sexual abuse. The film ties this to dissociation, and disembodiment. But it also has a message of the possibility of healing your sexuality despite the abuse. Now when you read the movie reviews and comments, this is where it gets really interesting. First, some of the words under the entire length &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-7LuNSHlPco&quot;&gt;movie on youtube&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I absolutely love this movie. I wish sci Fi was artistic like this, just pure creativity. It isn't like anything I ever seen, this movie actually is a inspiration in my artwork, still gotta practice but it's my main inspiration. It's so, random but it's not random? If that makes sense, it's a wonderful movie.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This commenter is pointing out how their subconscious is picking up on certain meanings without it landing fully in awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
My mom saw this movie in 1978ish at drive-in in Denver CO, I just watched it with her. She's in her 60s now, and she just kept saying  &quot;Wow...Wow!&quot;.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This movie activates hidden away parts that might have experienced sexual abuse, which would explain these strong reactions. Another set of comments that stands out is comments that point out that the commenter saw the movie as a kid and was scared and fascinated at the same time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I watched this when i was five I loved it so much this is so nostalgic
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Yall talking about how great this is, honestly traumatized by seeing it as a kid
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I can only be attracted to people who like this movie
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The comments under the trailer &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SgCxCZNkQ9E&quot;&gt;on youtube&lt;/a&gt; also give room for thought given the insights from above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I had vague memories of this film growing up, that would just pop into my head out of nowhere, or in my dreams a few times a year. I think I may have watched it when I was very young, and it just stuck. Until today, I always thought it was just a weird reoccurring dream. Pretty crazy that I just happened to stumble upon the trailer. I never even knew it was an actual movie.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This weird recurring dream might be this commenter expressing how deep in his subconscious certain traumatized parts of the mind were supressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
For anyone under the age of 5 this is a horror movie. Speaking from experience, those cold red eyes peer into my soul every night still.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
My god, this film is giving me emotions I can't even describe. I feel like I wanna a cry and curl up into a ball, terrified and amazed by the sheer beauty of the art, all the while giving me a type of anxiety I've never felt before
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might be someone describing how this movie activates buried memories of their own abuse. But they do not have it fully in their awareness and are therefore left with a lot of confusion about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I remembered when I was like 8 years old (that was in the 90's) and watched this film on TV all alone in the hall in the middle of the night. In that moment, it really seemed &quot;fascinating&quot; to me... yeah, also like... disturbing (lacking a better word) and ended with a feeling of emptiness... I don't know how to explain it... I'm happy to finally know the title of this film.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
This cartoon struck me like a ton of bricks when I was a kid.  The art style is so much like old scientific illustrations.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I remember seeing the trailer for this movie when I was maybe 4. It scarred me in ways I can't even explain and it's only when I actually saw it as an adult that I was able to make sense of what I had seen. 

This is not a kids movie.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Really awesome movie to watch on acid. Just not something you'd want to watch if you never watched a movie on acid before. This was the 3rd movie I ever saw on acid. (1st was yellow submarine movie by the beatles, 2nd was the wall movie by pink floyd.) It's mostly mesmerizing &amp;amp; serene. It has it's share of tense moments too, but  well worth it in the end. It really helped me learn to not give up on things so easily. Even when everything seem utterly hopeless.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I watched this movie when i was very kid, but I'll never forget it, a masterpiece...a dream telling, through dream languages, about reality ! 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I remember seeing this movie for some reason when I was a kid and it totally synced into my mind. I don’t remember going to see it in a movie theater I think it was actual TV back in the 70s. I don’t think that ever shows something like that where kids could see it. It’s probably created some really far out nightmares
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
This movie is so brilliant. I'm glad I watched it again. It freaked me out when I was little.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Amazing movie. A friend of mine told me to get ready for some &quot;disturbing shizzz&quot;, but that was not the case. The whole time I felt like this was the work of something from outer space, as if someone who's living this reality couldn't have come up with this. It had a blend of innocence and maturity, painting human life as primal as possible. Loved it. I was also high as shit.e.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
i've seen this madness last night in a bar. I just had the image without sound and i couldn't stop watching. Simply AMAZING
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I saw this as a child 
It made me scared of the world
Now that I am older I found out it was true!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
My parents took me to see this in the theater in 1973. I was 10. It traumatized me.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I remember my father showing me this movie when I was 7 years old and ending up semi-traumatised
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
This didn't scare me when I was young (about 8) and came across it when I was watching t.v., but now. It mortifies me. It REALLY freaks me out. I don't think I could ever watch it again. That fascinates me. I was so fearless as a child, but now, just the thought of watching this scares the hell out of me.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe this is not the movie this commenter is scared about, but their own experience this movie is pointing towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
There's something disturbing about this movie,but i cant get it out of my head.Genius
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Somehow, I can't shake off the impression this was real in some way.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This comment is truly amazing. It could be read as this person being somehow aware that this movie is pointing to their own experience of sexual abuse. But it is buried so deeply that they can not bring it into their awareness. Reading all the comments and making sense of them given this movie’s hidden meaning, we can speculate that these comments might point to the fact that, first of all, there are many people who have experienced sexual abuse that this movie resonates. Then also, the comments show how the human mind is very good at hiding this. The comments describe emotional experiences or point to how the movie traumatised or scared them. But to me, it seems likely that for many commenters, the movie is just pointing to their own experience, which is where these feelings come from. Then they watch the movie and resonate strongly, but without full awareness of what is going on. This, to me, seems to be best explained by trauma and dissociation. The memories are split off and buried deep inside the mind. When subtly triggered, as this movie does very well, these parts deep inside resonate. Because they are still very much suppressed, the viewers can’t make sense of the movie. It seems alien and weird and does not make sense. Yet they are captivated and in trance. All of this, to me, is an amazing insight how subtle and hidden signals are picked up on by the mind without coming fully into awareness. It’s influencing humans, captivating them, but they do not realize what is happening. It’s like they are not actually a single solid self. But they actually have hidden away parts that they can only faintly hear in the distance, so they don’t understand what they are communicating. I invite you to watch the movie and read through some reviews by film critics on Amazon, and comments on Youtube and try to make sense of this phenomenon. It’s eery how many people seem to miss this, almost as if they are prevented from seeing the child sexual abuse aspect of this film which has been around since the 70s. It shows how widespread this tragic phenomenon is and how much suppression the mind is capable of. This is how the mind works. We as humans are not these solid, monolithic selves. Especially when there is trauma, parts get split off, causing confusion. But just looking closely at this movie and its reception, we can see how normal this is. This also is an invitation to ponder and wonder more deeply, what are the things you are picking up on that draw in your interest, what people are picking up on beyond the obvious. Assuming people are truthful, and their minds sometimes or often strongly filter what they can be aware of. If you look closely and with curiosity there are a lot of surprising answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful for the openness of the internet that allows such peeks into so many different human minds. I’m grateful for this movie and the recommendation by my friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May you all find curiosity and wonder in your confusion. May you all move towards healing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marcus Ding</name></author><category term="[&quot;trauma&quot;, &quot;English&quot;]" /><category term="trauma" /><category term="movie" /><summary type="html">A friend recommended me the old sci-fi classic Fantastic Planet (link to the whole movie). This movie and its reception hold the key to understanding a lot of human behavior and functioning around dissociation, trauma, and human sexuality. It’s a great example of how mindful awareness and investigation help to understand something that possibly millions of humans who watched the movie did not fully piece together. I invite you to watch the film before reading the text.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Measures for more diversity in computer science</title><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/essay/2022/02/15/measures-for-more-diversity-in-computer-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Measures for more diversity in computer science" /><published>2022-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kryptokommun.ist/essay/2022/02/15/measures-for-more-diversity-in-computer-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kryptokommun.ist/essay/2022/02/15/measures-for-more-diversity-in-computer-science.html">&lt;p&gt;Intellectual people predominantly populate academia, natural sciences, and computer science. This makes sense and serves society as a whole; you need to do abstract thinking detached from emotions to find objective truth, flaws in your or others’ thinking, logic errors in your computer code. If you do study computer science, the goal of your computer science institute and professors is usually primarily to teach and train this intellectual mind, this abstract and logical thinking. That’s what makes you a computer scientist after all. I came to realize after a couple of years of studying computer sciences that all the lectures, exercises, research I was spending most of my waking time on were training a very narrow part of my human mind. My human experience relies on a much broader repertoire of modes of thinking and parts of my mind in everyday life. You have emotions, empathy, fear, wants, and needs expressed in the non-intellectual and non-abstract subconscious parts of the mind. These things make up the majority of experiencing being alive. But studying computer science focused me on a tiny part of my human mind, the abstract, intellectual, logical thinking. I was trained by spending and understanding this mode of thinking during my studies. It’s interesting to think about what effect this has on my mind if I spend so much time on a part of my mind that has so little to do with everyday human experience and satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is highly speculative, but let’s ask how this circumstance could impact diversity in computer science? And more important how could we then increase diversity in computer science? I refer to diversity in a broad sense, socio-economic, gender, nationality, ethnicity. From my experience, it’s fair to say that computer science has an above-average presence of neurodivergent humans, introverts, and a lack of social skills. This can go two ways; on the one hand, I have experienced environments of non-judgment, where nerds just nerd out and really do not care about social norms and therefore also create an inclusive environment, e.g., I’m thinking of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaos_Communication_Congress&quot;&gt;Chaos Communication Congress&lt;/a&gt; here. There you can see a lot of neurodivergence, cross-dressers, trans-humans walking the halls, and also a sense of everyone just being very open and friendly and helpful in ways I haven’t come across elsewhere. For example, when you are tearing something down at the end of the congress, random nerds will show up and offer to help you. The other way this nerdiness can swing is an environment where a lack of self-awareness, empathy, and ego comes together and creates an unempathetic, competitive, and cold climate. There can be dynamics of everyone trying to outsmart everyone else in a hostile instead of humble and caring manner. This is likely to make diverse people, who might identify with being in a weaker minority already, reconsider getting into such an environment. For example, I witnessed male nerds being irritated and, consequently, hurtful or demeaning towards women. They saw them primarily as women and as fellow human second. In conclusion, the question is how to leverage nerdiness to tip the scale towards the first way of the inclusive and non-judgemental environment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of goals come to mind that in my current understanding could increase diversity in computer science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Promote the values of humbleness, support, collaboration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase self-awareness and using the emotional mind and less lone wolf attitude.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Help everyone to decrease their ego and increase a sense of empathy towards others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support of otherness, questioning, and counter-culture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the follow-up question is how to get closer to these goals in academic institutions that teach computer science?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For group exercises, add tutors or coaches with high empathy and let them support the team building and relating in the groups. Tools like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eye_contact&quot;&gt;eye-gazing&lt;/a&gt;, talking about how you make each other feel, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dramaclassnow.com/?tag=trust-exercises&quot;&gt;trust-building&lt;/a&gt; exercises used in theater and improv classes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make emotional development a first-class citizen, support groups, and classes where understanding and regulating one’s emotions is taught. These should be fun and difficult at the same time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incorporate meditation teachers into the curriculum that teach basic mindfulness skills.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage professors and staff to mentor diverse students.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Marcus Ding</name></author><category term="[&quot;essay&quot;]" /><category term="tech" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="essay" /><category term="opinion" /><category term="english" /><summary type="html">Intellectual people predominantly populate academia, natural sciences, and computer science. This makes sense and serves society as a whole; you need to do abstract thinking detached from emotions to find objective truth, flaws in your or others’ thinking, logic errors in your computer code. If you do study computer science, the goal of your computer science institute and professors is usually primarily to teach and train this intellectual mind, this abstract and logical thinking. That’s what makes you a computer scientist after all. I came to realize after a couple of years of studying computer sciences that all the lectures, exercises, research I was spending most of my waking time on were training a very narrow part of my human mind. My human experience relies on a much broader repertoire of modes of thinking and parts of my mind in everyday life. You have emotions, empathy, fear, wants, and needs expressed in the non-intellectual and non-abstract subconscious parts of the mind. These things make up the majority of experiencing being alive. But studying computer science focused me on a tiny part of my human mind, the abstract, intellectual, logical thinking. I was trained by spending and understanding this mode of thinking during my studies. It’s interesting to think about what effect this has on my mind if I spend so much time on a part of my mind that has so little to do with everyday human experience and satisfaction.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does it make you feel more alive – A personal framework for approximatively evaluating ethics of technology as a user as well as technologist</title><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2022/01/24/does-it-make-you-feel-more-alive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does it make you feel more alive – A personal framework for approximatively evaluating ethics of technology as a user as well as technologist" /><published>2022-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2022/01/24/does-it-make-you-feel-more-alive</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2022/01/24/does-it-make-you-feel-more-alive.html">&lt;p&gt;I subscribe to the notion that ethics is entirely rational and maps to game theory. Ethics is about the principled resolution of conflicts of interest between autonomous agents under conditions of shared purpose when playing long games. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Plinz/status/1200189702919225344?s=20&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; With this in mind, it is crucial to model incentives and their consequences for systems to evaluate ethics. On the most general level, we can take the goal of avoiding suffering as the shared purpose of all humans on earth. Additionally, maintaining the global civilization might be another high-level goal. Technologists with the ability to create and change technological systems should do so ethically by considering these goals and projecting the impact of the system they create into the distant future. Making this difficult, the complexity of networks of human and non-human entities interacting through technology on a global scale has become overwhelming. Additionally, technology changes at such a fast pace that national and global elites cannot anticipate its full impact anymore, leading to increasing randomness in societies trajectories without anyone being able to formulate and implement a coherent plan projecting them into the future. Therefore it is even more critical that technologists evaluate the ethics and impacts of their actions, especially given the enormous leverage that computer technology offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A field that does evaluate the consequences of actions and systems and their incentives in a computational fashion is game theory, which considers the global and local outcomes, given that all actors act only on their local incentives. It allows analyzing games and creating rules for games such that desired outcomes are achieved. Climate change is a simple example of game theory and its relationship to ethics: Given a set of players, they can play two actions: polluting or not polluting. However, given that polluting is cheaper than not polluting, the optimal strategy for every player is to pollute. The problem is the incentive structure. Thus the concept of carbon footprint and shifting the responsibility of climate change to the individual is unethical since the incentives will be set up for everyone to keep polluting. Instead, a global entity needs to update the payout matrix of the players in such a way that the updated costs lead to behavior that optimizes for the global environmental costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking through the consequences of technology systems on these goals in a long game is cumbersome. Therefore I propose a simplified framework to approximate the ethics of technological systems locally. It is based on the observation that a lot of the dark side of deploying computer technologies seems to be about it being used to control human behavior by offering short-term and shallow fulfillment of human needs and desires. Often technology is used to control humans, treating them more like machines instead of helping them to be more human. As a user, you could ask yourself: “Does this in the long term help me feel more alive and human?”. As a technologist, you could ask yourself: “Does this in the long term help users feel more alive and human?”. While this question is quite open for interpretation, I propose referring to the five hindrances mentioned in Buddhistic scripture that are said to hinder progress in meditation and daily life. Technology that does increase the strength of the five hindrances (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_hindrances&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;) in its users could be said to contribute to them feeling less alive and human in the long term:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sensory desire: seeking for pleasure through the five senses of sight, sound, smell, taste and physical feeling.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ill-will: feelings of hostility, resentment, hatred and bitterness.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sloth-and-torpor: half-hearted action with little or no effort or concentration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restlessness-and-worry: the inability to calm the mind and focus one’s energy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doubt: lack of conviction or trust in one’s abilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us apply this framework to a few examples from the user side. As a first example, let us look at some features of the Instagram iOS app. When I want to search for something, I have to open the search screen (see image below), which offers a small search bar at the top and the rest of the screen filled with images and videos curated by an automatic recommender system. Does this usage of technology make me feel more alive and human? No, it mostly does not. First of all, this unwanted recommendation directly subverts my intent of wanting to search for something, which already is undermining me exercising my will. Second, to a large degree, the recommended content is superficial posts that are optimized for engagement. A picture of a beautiful woman with an inspiring caption will not boost my mood in the long term and is just a technological knock-off version of a physical world one-to-one human interaction that inspires me. Also, the asymmetry of the following concept makes for a less human experience compared to the real world. Since the recommended content is mostly by accounts with a larger following which optimize for engagement. Interacting with that account will entail receiving less attention than I put in due to the asymmetric situation when users with large followings interact with their followers. This example shows that the app contributes to increasing hindrances one, three, and four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/instagram-search-screen.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Instagram iOS search screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is video calling, which is part of the Instagram app and many other apps. Video calling facilitates a symmetric, real-time communication channel between two or more users. Even though this mode of communication lacks the elements of touch, smell, body language, and high-resolution of physical world interactions, it makes up for this by keeping human interaction possible over large distances. Additionally, to hearing the voice with all its emotional subtleties, I can see the other person and their facial expressions approximating a physical world human interaction. Keeping in touch with friends I value and otherwise would only get to interact within the physical world a couple of times a year makes me feel more human and alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us look at 3D printing, a technology that allows volumetric printing of shapes from digital 3D models. This allows processing digital intangible 3D models into physical world objects that I can touch and use. Overall this makes me feel more human and alive. I can have an idea or look at someone else’s idea for a 3D model and then print it out and get a sense of the idea with much more senses than the current restriction to a 2D view on a screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are technologies for which this framework is not sufficient for evaluation since they are too abstract and general to be evaluated personally. For example, Javascript can be used to create interactive Web apps that engage more and help me understand a machine learning algorithm by displaying a visual model I can step through, which feels livelier and more human than reading from a static book. Then also, Javascript can be used to surveil and record my usage of the Facebook site, which is used to maximize engagement leading to an inevitable race to the bottom of the brain stem. &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigthink.com/high-culture/tristan-harris-the-attention-economy-a-race-to-the-bottom-of-the-brain-stem/&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; This ultimately engages me short-term, but long-term glues my attention to the screen, making me feel less alive and human.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marcus Ding</name></author><category term="[&quot;tech&quot;]" /><category term="tech" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="essay" /><category term="opinion" /><category term="english" /><summary type="html">I subscribe to the notion that ethics is entirely rational and maps to game theory. Ethics is about the principled resolution of conflicts of interest between autonomous agents under conditions of shared purpose when playing long games. [1] With this in mind, it is crucial to model incentives and their consequences for systems to evaluate ethics. On the most general level, we can take the goal of avoiding suffering as the shared purpose of all humans on earth. Additionally, maintaining the global civilization might be another high-level goal. Technologists with the ability to create and change technological systems should do so ethically by considering these goals and projecting the impact of the system they create into the distant future. Making this difficult, the complexity of networks of human and non-human entities interacting through technology on a global scale has become overwhelming. Additionally, technology changes at such a fast pace that national and global elites cannot anticipate its full impact anymore, leading to increasing randomness in societies trajectories without anyone being able to formulate and implement a coherent plan projecting them into the future. Therefore it is even more critical that technologists evaluate the ethics and impacts of their actions, especially given the enormous leverage that computer technology offers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creating a FreeCAD 3D view inside Jupyter Notebooks - GSoC 2020</title><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2020/08/31/google-summer-of-code.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creating a FreeCAD 3D view inside Jupyter Notebooks - GSoC 2020" /><published>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2020/08/31/google-summer-of-code</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2020/08/31/google-summer-of-code.html">&lt;p&gt;Accidentally while &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?f=24&amp;amp;t=48957&quot;&gt;creating a lamp&lt;/a&gt; I ended up learning &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freecadweb.org&quot;&gt;FreeCAD&lt;/a&gt;. FreeCAD is an amazing open source &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer-aided_design&quot;&gt;CAD program&lt;/a&gt;. It still amazes me that people created this for free in their spare time. The software is still in it’s alpha version and is far from perfect as you can tell by the current release version number 0.19 and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?t=43461&quot;&gt;heated discussions&lt;/a&gt; around how soon a 1.0 release could be reached. Still it’s very usable and once you get the gist of it you can create powerful and complex designs. FreeCADs approach to CAD is a parametric design. That means that you specify shapes with parameters. E.g. you base the 3D shape on a 2D drawing. The geometric figures of the 2D drawing - circles, recatangles, lines - are all constrained with parameters. Then you create a 3D shape out of your 2D sketch, for example by extruding it. And every step is based on certain parameters that can reference previous parameters. It’s basically visual programming. Is FreeCAD &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/NP-Vollständigkeit&quot;&gt;NP-complete&lt;/a&gt;? Probably, but that’s a topic for another time. Anyways. The parametric approach allows you to easily modify your design at any time just by tuning these parameters. For example with my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kryptokommunist/tolv&quot;&gt;lamp design&lt;/a&gt; the number of aluminium bars is a parameter I can simply tweak at any point in time. All the relevant details depending on this number will be automatically recomputed by FreeCAD. This gives great flexibility and allows for fast customization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com&quot;&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; (GSoC) is a program run by Google that gives stipends to students who over a period of three months implement an open source project with a mentor organization. Among the organizations are well known ones like Arduino, Ruby or Wikimedia. But there are also more niche organizations that are not so widely known. The great part about GSoC is that students apply for specific projects, so you yourself determine how exciting the thing you work on is if you get accepted. This and the work from home aspects are definitely something a lot of internships can’t offer. For me it started with seeing the potential of first designing a parametric lamp and then creating a custom web page where you could change the parameters to your liking and see a live 3D rendering of the changed lamp. Then you just download the 3D files and 3D-print the lamp. I was heavily inspired by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://card10-cover.0x1b.de/index.php&quot;&gt;card1o cover generator&lt;/a&gt; created with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openscad.org&quot;&gt;OpenSCAD&lt;/a&gt;. After some research I realized that something comparable to rendering OpenSCAD in the web browser does not exist for FreeCAD yet. I already knew about GSoC and to my suprise FreeCAD was one of the open source organizations taking part in GSoC 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/card1o_badge.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The result from printing the cover generator customized &lt;a href=&quot;https://card10.badge.events.ccc.de&quot;&gt;card1o badge&lt;/a&gt; cover. It's such a cool experience to customize something so effortlessly and to then have it in your hands. Unlike designing everything you don't have to think a about it too much, but you still feel more connected to the end product since it has a personal touch. That's the experience I wanted to create for my lamp design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sent out two applications: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1VgfsD06Qvb87S-tQazfTsyYTp14Z3EjF4V9puPVNCTQ/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;A better IPython and Jupyter Notebook Integration for FreeCAD&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1lxe3MTVMQYnv6r3W7KuuzcKgY_rLS2Qgd6FjZlstwaU/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Measurement tool for FreeCAD&lt;/a&gt;. In the end the first one was chosen. It was closer to my original idea that got me excited and on the path of applying. I definitely didn’t expect the application to succeed, but that might just be the classic imposter syndrome. I put in quite some thought researching the topic and contacted some of the previous students, I even managed to email the student who applied for the exact same idea a couple years before. He was so nice to send me a link to his old application so that I could make us of the feedback he got on his application from back then. After the acceptance the project started moving. The FreeCAD community is mainly organized in an old school internet forum. I haven’t used one since I was active on an RC car forum when I was 14 before I signed up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.freecadweb.org&quot;&gt;forum.freecadweb.org&lt;/a&gt;. Here is the project thread where I posted questions and updates on work progress: &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?f=8&amp;amp;t=46039&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;. For the unlikely case that you haven’t read through my 8 page project application let me summarize it for you. Or actually the document is very well written so let me quote it instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Currently, FreeCAD’s IPython and Jupyter Notebook integration can only provide visualization by running the entire FreeCAD GUI alongside the notebook. Besides not being elegant it brings many problems with it, like not being able to save the visualizations inside the notebook for sharing or bringing visual complexity of the entire GUI into the view instead of just displaying the 3D model. It is therefore important to find a way to visualize FreeCAD’s 3D scene in the IPython display system as supported by Jupyter Notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Tackling the open issue &lt;a href=&quot;https://tracker.freecadweb.org/view.php?id=2869&quot;&gt;“IPython / Jupyter support”&lt;/a&gt; I aim to implement a IPython compatible visualization of FreeCAD’s 3D Open Inventor scene graph. To achieve this I intend to choose a suitable JavaScript library able to render a 3D scene graph and to implement a mapping between it and the Open Inventor scene graph. After this as a byproduct I want to implement a better WebGL export based on the scene graph instead of document objects as currently found in FreeCAD. For this I can reuse and integrate the scene graph mapping component. Lastly I want to document the results in the Wiki and create an example Jupyter notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make things a bit more clear, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyter.org&quot;&gt;Juypter Notebook&lt;/a&gt; is an multi purpose computation evironment, which basically means you can run interactive code on the web. Since Juypter Notebook and FreeCAD both support Python this is a match made in heaven. With Jupyter you can quickly create interactive UIs and mix them with text into a great experience for learning, communicating and experimenting. Opening this space to FreeCAD users and developers brings potentially endless new possibilities. You get access to all the powerful Jupyter widgets that make it so popular. I certainly hope some of you reading this will take this idea further by writing that interactive Python scripting tutorial inside a notebook, by writing that new workbench which will have a widget for notebooks, by improving your workbenches Python API so you can easily access all GUI functions inside a notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/jupyterpreview.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&quot;The Jupyter Notebook is an open-source web application that allows you to create and share documents that contain live code, equations, visualizations and narrative text. Uses include: data cleaning and transformation, numerical simulation, statistical modeling, data visualization, machine learning, and much more.&quot; (Quote and image from &lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyter.org&quot;&gt;juypter.org&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this GSoC I successfully implemented a 3D viewer that can display FreeCAD objects inside a notebook. Currently it’s still limited to the Part Workbench, I still have to implement modifications to handle scene objects created by other workbenches. The current project is a good base to build upon. The basic features working right now are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;displaying FreeCAD scene graph face sets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;displaying FreeCAD scene graph line sets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setting view parameters according to FreeCAD scene graph
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;position&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;rotation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;metalness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;transparency&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;color&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;emissive color&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;highlighting FreeCAD object faces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;selecting FreeCAD object faces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;displaying FreeCAD object edges indices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;selecting FreeCAD object edges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;displaying FreeCAD object faces indices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rotating the view&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;zooming the view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There obviously are many more features that should be implemented over time to make this project maximally useful. For example moving the view, view controls matching the FreeCAD key combinations and having the standard FreeCAD view buttons (“top”, “bottom”, etc.) available would be great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gsoc-2020-interactivity-demo.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;It's not much, but it's honest work. This project demo shows the benefits of using the Jupyter Notebook environment. You can quickly code an interactive UI that creates objects in a FreeCAD document and removes them again. Also you can see that the viewer will tell you the index of faces and edges. This is important if you want to script FreeCAD entirely in a notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example Jupyter Notebook that uses the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;freecadviewer&lt;/code&gt; Python module I created during the GSoC. Be aware that due to the missing Python kernel (this is just a static site) most of the interactivity is lost. For full interactivity you should run &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kryptokommunist/Jupyter_FreeCAD/blob/7dc507e295525909668996adf47bb0df68950fdf/FreeCAD%20inside%20Jupyter%20Notebook%20-%20Examples.ipynb&quot;&gt;the notebook&lt;/a&gt; yourself. The link to the full static notebook is &lt;a href=&quot;/google-summer-of-code-2020&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. But still you can pan and zoom the 3D views inside the notebook. Also I recommend viewing this on a bigger screen than a smartphone, even though mobile works, it’s not ideal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe height=&quot;800&quot; src=&quot;/google-summer-of-code-2020&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As you probably already have guessed, this enables you to embed interactive FreeCAD views on your web sites, e.g. like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe height=&quot;770&quot; src=&quot;/embedding-single-widget-gsoc-2020-demo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You get this cool feature almost for free thanks to Jupyter and without touching any Javascript. I created an example notebook to illustrate the process and potential. The link to the full static notebook is &lt;a href=&quot;/embedding-single-widget-gsoc-2020&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe height=&quot;800&quot; src=&quot;/embedding-single-widget-gsoc-2020&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But enough with the “Why” let’s get to the “How” aka technical details shall we? Since the goal is to have a very general 3D viewer solution that will be able to display any content that exists inside the desktop applications 3D view we need to work directly with it’s scene graph. So how does FreeCAD generate it’s 3D view? Internally FreeCAD relies on a C++ CAD library called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opencascade.com/content/overview&quot;&gt;Open Cascade&lt;/a&gt; that implements 2D and 3D geometric modelling. You could say Open Cascade is FreeCADs CAD kernel. Internally Open Cascade represents Geometries mathematically in potentially infinite resulution. The visualization on the other hand is realized with a probably not that widely know framework called &lt;a href=&quot;https://coin3d.github.io&quot;&gt;Coin3D&lt;/a&gt; which itself is based on a format called Open Inventor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Coin is an OpenGL-based, 3D graphics library that has its roots in the Open Inventor 2.1 API, which Coin still is compatible with.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;If you are not familiar with Open Inventor, it is a scene-graph based, retain-mode, rendering and model manipulation, C++ class library, originally designed by SGI. It quickly became the de facto standard graphics library for 3D visualization and visual simulation software in the scientific and engineering community after its release. It also became the basis for the VRML1 file format standard. Several books exists on the subject of Open Inventor, most notably The Inventor Mentor, and The Inventor Toolmaker, both highly recommended for those who wants to learn how to use Open Inventor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully someone started creating a Python binding for the Coin3D library as a topic for his masterthesis. It still lives on under the name &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/coin3d/pivy&quot;&gt;pivy&lt;/a&gt;. This means that I possibly can implement the project entirely in Python. Which has been a very pleasent language to work with so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this the plan was to extract the objects from the Coin3D scene graph and to then translate and represent them within a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebGL&quot;&gt;WebGL&lt;/a&gt; based library that can be used inside a Jupyter notebook. This meant I might have to touch JavaScript which is not a beauty to work with. After some deliberations I chose &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jupyter-widgets/pythreejs&quot;&gt;pythreejs&lt;/a&gt; which is a Jupyter Notebook extension that integrates the infamous &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mrdoob/three.js&quot;&gt;ThreeJS&lt;/a&gt; with a Python bridge. That meant less JavaScript and a smooth integration into the Jupyter Notebook environment. My previous experiments with directly inserting the ThreeJS JavaScript library all failed horribly. Additionally this means that FreeCAD users and developers already familiar with scripting in Python can modify the Jupyter 3D view themselves with a minimal learning curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end the task was not extremely complex. All I needed to do was to extract faces and edges from the Coin3D scene graph and then reassemble it in a slightly modified structure inside pythreejs. The fundamental structure between both 3D libraries is similar enough that I can represent Coin3D in ThreeJS without major changes. What still made this project a challenge was starting from zero knowledge about FreeCADs internals and computer graphics. Additionally some bugs alsways make their way into the project and finding and solving them can take a lot of time. Especially the notebook environment was new for me and made some aspects more complicated. For examples you now also have to take a look at the Javascript console in the browser from time to time to diagnose a problem. Also coordination and communication with many stake holder slows down the progress and it can be especially frustrating if you think you found a bug and then the project is not maintained regularly and you have to watch your &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jupyter-widgets/pythreejs/issues/329&quot;&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jupyter-widgets/pythreejs/issues/331&quot;&gt;die silently&lt;/a&gt; on Github. Overall it’s still a great experience to work so autonomously on for an open source project that is used by so many people. So I hope there will be some people interested in using FreeCAD inside Jupyter Notebook as well out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue to improve the project in the future. You can find the repository &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kryptokommunist/Jupyter_FreeCAD&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you use the module and encounter any issues or just find it useful, don’t hesitate to post to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?f=8&amp;amp;t=46039&quot;&gt;forum thread&lt;/a&gt; or let me know with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kryptokommunist&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; or an issue in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kryptokommunist/Jupyter_FreeCAD&quot;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to my mentors: &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.freecadweb.org/memberlist.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;amp;u=686&quot;&gt;@ickby&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thekurtwk&quot;&gt;@kkremitzki&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/yorikvanhavre&quot;&gt;@yorik&lt;/a&gt;. I’m grateful for them spending time on helping me with the project. Doing this entirely in their spare time is insanely great! Also thanks to the entire FreeCAD community who gave helpful input. I was especially impressed by how much effort &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/3569&quot;&gt;@vocx-fc&lt;/a&gt; put into reviewing my second pull request to FreeCAD. So this GSoC, also by watching what my fellow students where doing, definitely taught me to appreciate free software and open source even more. ❤️&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marcus Ding</name></author><category term="[&quot;tech&quot;]" /><category term="tech" /><category term="gsoc" /><category term="opensource" /><category term="freecad" /><category term="english" /><summary type="html">Accidentally while creating a lamp I ended up learning FreeCAD. FreeCAD is an amazing open source CAD program. It still amazes me that people created this for free in their spare time. The software is still in it’s alpha version and is far from perfect as you can tell by the current release version number 0.19 and the heated discussions around how soon a 1.0 release could be reached. Still it’s very usable and once you get the gist of it you can create powerful and complex designs. FreeCADs approach to CAD is a parametric design. That means that you specify shapes with parameters. E.g. you base the 3D shape on a 2D drawing. The geometric figures of the 2D drawing - circles, recatangles, lines - are all constrained with parameters. Then you create a 3D shape out of your 2D sketch, for example by extruding it. And every step is based on certain parameters that can reference previous parameters. It’s basically visual programming. Is FreeCAD NP-complete? Probably, but that’s a topic for another time. Anyways. The parametric approach allows you to easily modify your design at any time just by tuning these parameters. For example with my lamp design the number of aluminium bars is a parameter I can simply tweak at any point in time. All the relevant details depending on this number will be automatically recomputed by FreeCAD. This gives great flexibility and allows for fast customization. Google Summer of Code (GSoC) is a program run by Google that gives stipends to students who over a period of three months implement an open source project with a mentor organization. Among the organizations are well known ones like Arduino, Ruby or Wikimedia. But there are also more niche organizations that are not so widely known. The great part about GSoC is that students apply for specific projects, so you yourself determine how exciting the thing you work on is if you get accepted. This and the work from home aspects are definitely something a lot of internships can’t offer. For me it started with seeing the potential of first designing a parametric lamp and then creating a custom web page where you could change the parameters to your liking and see a live 3D rendering of the changed lamp. Then you just download the 3D files and 3D-print the lamp. I was heavily inspired by the card1o cover generator created with OpenSCAD. After some research I realized that something comparable to rendering OpenSCAD in the web browser does not exist for FreeCAD yet. I already knew about GSoC and to my suprise FreeCAD was one of the open source organizations taking part in GSoC 2020. The result from printing the cover generator customized card1o badge cover. It's such a cool experience to customize something so effortlessly and to then have it in your hands. Unlike designing everything you don't have to think a about it too much, but you still feel more connected to the end product since it has a personal touch. That's the experience I wanted to create for my lamp design.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">HPI Startup Bootcamp</title><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/startup/english/2020/02/15/hpi-startup-bootcamp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HPI Startup Bootcamp" /><published>2020-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kryptokommun.ist/startup/english/2020/02/15/hpi-startup-bootcamp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kryptokommun.ist/startup/english/2020/02/15/hpi-startup-bootcamp.html">&lt;p&gt;This year and last year I was lucky to be part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hpi.de/entrepreneurship/veranstaltungen/startup-bootcamps.html&quot;&gt;HPI Startup Bootcamp&lt;/a&gt;. To my suprise my team won the first time I took part (&lt;a href=&quot;https://hpi.de/entrepreneurship/veranstaltungen/startup-bootcamps/hpi-startup-bootcamp-2018.html&quot;&gt;link or it didn’t happen&lt;/a&gt;) and last year at least got a spontaneous made up prize because the jury liked the idea so much (&lt;a href=&quot;https://hpi.de/entrepreneurship/veranstaltungen/startup-bootcamps/hpi-startup-bootcamp-2019.html&quot;&gt;can I has link plz&lt;/a&gt;). But enough humble or not so humble brags. I wanted to condense what I have learned there into a text hopefully giving you guidance on whether to attend and what to expect at such an event aside from late Roman, decadent catering. The learnings are a combination of the practical bootcamp experiences as well as the accompanying lecture called &lt;a href=&quot;https://hpi.de/entrepreneurship/veranstaltungen/it-entrepreneurship-vorlesung.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;IT-Entrepreneurship&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hpi_startup_bootcamp_all.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Lots of people and obligatory branded T-shirts. (image: HPI / Kay Herschelmann)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;practical-experience-from-speakers&quot;&gt;Practical Experience from Speakers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most inspiring and motivating aspect is the wide array of guest speakers that speak about their own failures and success on the startup journey. The key take away from that for myself was that they were just normal people that just did stuff and never stopped trying. Some founded over a dozen companies that eventually failed before becoming part of the winning team. Also people founded companies early in their life but some even started at 40 and succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also many admitted that luck played a big part in the ultimate success. They hit a right trend, a growing market segment, some unlucky competitor went bankrupt or a huge company just somehow never bothered to develop a competing product. And clearly there were some that had a very noble mission and they were clearly striving to make the world better with their product and companies while others were more driven by success and more control over company culture than the actual product and it’s impact in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also talking to people from the Venture Capital world was interesting a guy that about every four sentences was saying “You need to ask where’s the money!” comes to mind. Also tales of how complicated regulatory rules for creating medical devices in Germany are were part of the learnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;team&quot;&gt;Team&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hpi_startup_bootcamp_team.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;This is how a team could look like. (image: HPI / Kay Herschelmann)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The founding team for a startup is essential for its survival. Since resources are scarce in the beginning the team will have to put up with a lot of pressure and needs to solve hard problems in a fast changing environment. The ideal size for a founding team is two to three people. Due to lack of resources and the necessity of fast execution the team members should know each other well so they can judge if they trust each other to manage to deliver in a startup setting. Furthermore the team should consist of smart and driven people, mediocre teams won’t build a great company. A complementary skill set also makes a good team, so there’s someone that is good at marketing and business, design and UX as well as someone comfortable with engineering and developing (Along the lines of Hipster, Hacker, Hustler).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideal team for my startup would consist of one person with a business background who also has a very good understanding of the technology or sector the idea focuses on. This person should be able to understand and communicate complex ideas to a non-technical audience and have excellent people skills. Further the team should have a person that is highly technically competent. Additionally one person on the team should have competency in building front-end applications and graphics programming. All of these people would ideally already know each other for a while and be self-motivated and believing in the company’s mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;startup-idea&quot;&gt;Startup Idea&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two idea generation methods for startup ideas: &lt;em&gt;Problem Identification&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Technology Push&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Technology Push&lt;/em&gt; describes the process of pushing a new or existing technology out into the market for a use-case that currently is not addressed by the technology. Problem Identification on the other hand describes the reversed process of first identifying a problem by market research and observing users and then building a solution to the identified problem. Using your own problems is generally not recommended since you might be biased and the needs and requirements of yourself don’t have to reflect the needs and requirements of the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my startup idea I used the &lt;em&gt;Technology Push&lt;/em&gt; approach. This was due to my own interest in the field of audio processing and having some technical experience within it. I did some cursory research and saw that there was no existing commercial audification player. Therefore my reasoning was, that this might be an idea that is not too obvious but at the same time possibly very useful to some use-cases. Even though the idea was inspired by Rolls-Royce’s bootcamp challenge, the hope is that this technology has a broader market beyond just addressing this particular problem. Therefore I’d categorize it as &lt;em&gt;Technology Push&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;leap-of-faith-hypotheses&quot;&gt;Leap of Faith Hypotheses&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With every new startup there are new ideas and &lt;em&gt;leap of faith hypotheses&lt;/em&gt;. These are assumptions that you implicitly assume to be true without having actually tested them. For example with the &lt;em&gt;iPod&lt;/em&gt; there was the implicit assumption that most people would pay for digital music. Making these hypotheses explicit and methodically testing them will help you steer your startup into the right direction and avoid suffering from confirmation biases. It makes sense to differentiate between two kinds of leap of faith hypothesis: value and growth hypothesis. The value hypothesis concern the value provided to users by your product while growth hypothesis refer to growth assumptions. For my startup idea from the 2019 bootcamp these hypotheses were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/leap_of_faith_hypothesis.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The idea was audification of data streams in order to enable human data analysts to intuitively grasp what's going on in multidimensional data sets. Since you can process parallel sounds much more efficiently than multiple visual graphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;interviews&quot;&gt;Interviews&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to ground your product in reality and to reach customer and market fit it is beneficial to get external input through customer interviews. The main goal is to identify your specific customers needs, beware of the fact that what a customer says she wants and the actual need she has might not be related. The fundamentals of the customer interview are to stick and develop an interview script beforehand. Further you should ask for sufficient time. Lastly it is vital to immediately afterwards document the interview. The interviews should get you feedback for different phases of your startup. First in your beginning and ideation phase the &lt;em&gt;Problem Interview&lt;/em&gt; will help you to get a clearer picture of the problem and environment you chose. Next when you build a demo to address your problem a &lt;em&gt;Solution Interview&lt;/em&gt; will help you get feedback before starting to build the actual problem. And finally when you build your first product, your &lt;em&gt;MVP&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;MVP Interview&lt;/em&gt; you should test your messaging, pricing and activation flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;business-models&quot;&gt;Business Models&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three common business models are: &lt;em&gt;Direct Business Model&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Multisided Business Model&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Marketplaces&lt;/em&gt;. A &lt;em&gt;Direct Business Model&lt;/em&gt; advertises and sells directly to the user who pays for the product as its user. Different from that is a &lt;em&gt;Multisided Business Model&lt;/em&gt;, where the main users of a product pay indirectly, non monetarily while the monetization happens through another party paying for a derivative asset of the product, e.g. Facebook’s monetization of its users through selling ads. Slightly similar is the &lt;em&gt;Marketplace Business Model&lt;/em&gt; where buyers and sellers are matched through your product and the value exchange between them is direct unlike in advertising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;lean-startup-approach&quot;&gt;Lean Startup Approach&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Build-Measure-Learn Cycle&lt;/em&gt; concept sees the startup as a machine that turns ideas into products and adapts quickly to learned lessons in order to create a successful product. This process can be seen as an iterative cycle with six stages: &lt;em&gt;Ideas, Build, Product, Measure, Data, Learn&lt;/em&gt;. With each Iteration of the process new learnings arise that will steer the decisions of the startup. This concept is similar to the Agile process or Design Thinking process with fast feedback and prototyping iterations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;offering-and-minimal-viable-product-mvp&quot;&gt;Offering and Minimal-Viable-Product (MVP)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to validate the &lt;em&gt;Problem-Solution-Fit&lt;/em&gt; you can use an offering. The offering is a test used to measure not what users say, but what they actually do. It consists of an &lt;em&gt;Unique Value Proposition, Demo&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Pricing&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;Unique Value Proposition&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;UVP&lt;/em&gt;) is a promise about your solution to the customers. The Demo is an narrative that takes your &lt;em&gt;UVP&lt;/em&gt; and helps potential customers visualize and grasp it. The Pricing is an call to action that might even require an actual payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;MVP&lt;/em&gt; is a product comprised out of the minimum set of features in order to learn from early adopters. The goal is to enable fast iterations and early customer feedback to avoid building something that nobody wants. The difference to an offering is that an offering is not an actual product but a carefully scripted narrative about the product and not an functional product. The &lt;em&gt;MVP&lt;/em&gt; on the other hand is a functional product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;MVP&lt;/em&gt; for my startup would be an application that can load &lt;em&gt;CSV&lt;/em&gt; files from disk and output an audification whilst simultaneously showing the graphs so you can verify and understand that you are actually hearing the data characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;business-model-environment&quot;&gt;Business Model Environment&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key forces influencing the business model are: &lt;em&gt;Key Trends, Market Forces, Macro Economic Forces and Industry Forces&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Key Trends&lt;/em&gt; are general trends in various fields, they can be regulatory, societal, technological and more. &lt;em&gt;Market Forces&lt;/em&gt; are issues, needs and demands, segments of your market and similar items. &lt;em&gt;Macro Economic Forces&lt;/em&gt; relate to global economy, it’s infrastructure, commodity resources etc.. &lt;em&gt;Industry Forces&lt;/em&gt; consist of your competitors, your supply chain, substitute products and other examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;startup-marketing---aarrr-metrics&quot;&gt;Startup Marketing - AARRR Metrics&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;AARRR Metrics&lt;/em&gt; are an acronym referring to &lt;em&gt;Acquisition, Activation, Retention, Referral&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Revenue&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Acquisition Metrics&lt;/em&gt; are all related to where the users of the product are coming from what channels, what costs etc.. &lt;em&gt;Activation Metrics&lt;/em&gt; are about the first experience the user has with the product, at what point do you gain users to permanently use you product and show them the worth of it. &lt;em&gt;Retention Metrics&lt;/em&gt; measure what customers you are loosing and the reasons for that. &lt;em&gt;Referral Metrics&lt;/em&gt; measure why and how users become advocates for your product. &lt;em&gt;Revenue Metrics&lt;/em&gt; measure &lt;em&gt;Customer Lifetime Value&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Customer Acquisition Cost&lt;/em&gt; and other revenue related metrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: Startup bootcamps can be fun and you learn some things that prepare you for the real thing, but you still have to go out and just start moving!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marcus Ding</name></author><category term="[&quot;startup&quot;, &quot;english&quot;]" /><category term="hpi" /><category term="startup" /><summary type="html">This year and last year I was lucky to be part of the HPI Startup Bootcamp. To my suprise my team won the first time I took part (link or it didn’t happen) and last year at least got a spontaneous made up prize because the jury liked the idea so much (can I has link plz). But enough humble or not so humble brags. I wanted to condense what I have learned there into a text hopefully giving you guidance on whether to attend and what to expect at such an event aside from late Roman, decadent catering. The learnings are a combination of the practical bootcamp experiences as well as the accompanying lecture called IT-Entrepreneurship.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Travel tips – learn from my mistakes</title><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/travel/2019/03/21/travel-tips-learn-from-my-mistakes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Travel tips – learn from my mistakes" /><published>2019-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kryptokommun.ist/travel/2019/03/21/travel-tips-learn-from-my-mistakes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kryptokommun.ist/travel/2019/03/21/travel-tips-learn-from-my-mistakes.html">&lt;p&gt;I love travelling, every now and then I have the privilege to be able to travel abroad for a longer period. In my case that usually has been about a month. And things go horribly wrong. On the one hand it means I learn something on the other hand it means things like burning 700 Euros for no other reason than being utterly stupid. Therefore I compiled this compact post about how to do things right from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;do-you-even-prepare-bro&quot;&gt;Do you even prepare bro?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparing a trip is something I’d rather avoid doing, it’s just not any fun. I once was asked by a guy on the street if he could crash my couch. As it turned out he was travelling without anything. No money, no plan, not even a backpack. He was basically homeless, just with a drive to explore the world, which made all the difference. All he had was his T-shirt, pants, shoes and most importantly: His willingness to leave his comfort zone. &lt;!--more--&gt;He’d been doing it for years successfully. So of course I’d let him crash my couch. But since me and you aren’t that badass, unlike this inspiring fella, we need some preparation before taking off. Still he is living proof, how far you can get with literally nothing. So next time you get anxious about something, think of the guy that by default arrives with prospects of sleeping under the bridge but still manages to find a home to sleep (admittedly not always) and to enjoy his travels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;booking-flights&quot;&gt;Booking flights&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just don’t be a no-show for your outbound flight assuming you can just book a later one separately. Most airlines cheapest tickets don’t allow this and your return trip gets automatically cancelled. As a result I burned 700 Euros for buying new plane tickets. Therefore always check with the airline about cancellation/rebooking and no-show conditions because plane tickets are not sensible. Also make sure that you have check-in luggage included if you have multi destination flights. Consider buying that slightly more expensive ticket with a cancellation option if you aren’t one hundred percent sure about the travel date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;preparing-for-the-worst-case-before-your-trip&quot;&gt;Preparing for the worst case before your trip&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are the bad things that can happen to you while travelling. Things where you’d go: “I’m so fucked! I’m so fucked! God, I am so fucked!”. You could get robbed, you could end up in a situation where every store is already closed and you’re starving. You could loose all your cash, you could loose your credit card. All these scenarios can reasonably happen and some I experienced myself. Therefore it is smart to prepare beforehand to at least mitigate some of the fallback of getting yourself in a messy situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bring a food ration that’s enough for 3 days, I highly recommend very compact powder food, e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://jimmyjoy.com&quot;&gt;Jimmy Joy&lt;/a&gt;. Tastes good and can really save your ass.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bring enough cash to survive for 3 days, even if it’s just in your own currency. You can change it at an money exchange.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get information on how to report a lost credit card to your bank. If you know the phone number: If you can’t call them how can you do it with just internet?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find out what options you have if you lost your credit card. Does your bank provide you emergency cash and credit card? If not you should switch your bank. I can fully recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dkb.de/privatkunden/visa-card/&quot;&gt;DKB-Visa&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a VoIP-number so you can make cheap phone calls to your bank or travel-insurance or other important institutions at your home country without going bankrupt. I recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.satellite.me&quot;&gt;Satellite&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll get 100 minutes for free!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure you have a travel insurance and that they cover the country your visiting. If not it’s no more than 10 Euros a year so you don’t have to worry about getting sick or injured abroad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check if you should get special vaccinations for your destination. Sometimes your regular insurance will cover the costs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To prevent getting lost if you need to catch the last bus or to return your rented snow board gear, make sure to have offline maps and enough battery or as a backup a paper map.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/travel_tips_food.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;My breakfast, lunch and dinner after loosing my credit card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%; display:block; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto; &quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/travel_tips_wallet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lol&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;I lost my credit card before arriving in Tokyo. This was all the cash I had arriving at my hotel. All in all it was just enough to buy tickets from the airport to the hotel and the next Western Union branch next day after organizing emergency cash. I could not even afford a bottle of water.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/travel_tips_money.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Emergency cash provided by Visa same day after calling them over VoIP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/travel_tips_credit_card.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Emergency credit card provided by Visa two days after calling them, it was directly sent to my hotel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;keeping-things-so-you-can-quickly-access-them&quot;&gt;Keeping things so you can quickly access them&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Packing my bag inevitably led to chaos. Imagine the following scenario: Your on the train, you need to look up your next connection. Your phones battery is close to dying a painless but consequential death. You open your backpack and you hectically sort through the clutter. You’re getting stressed, your body emits stress hormones and as a result you die 5 years earlier than without this stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the solution, use see-through bags you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.de/dp/B07DFD2NNJ/&quot;&gt;get on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;. I sort everything in categories. E.g. important travel documents (passport, plane tickets), hygiene, plane utensils (sleeping mask, ear plugs) etc. This way you can quick access everything you need in seconds. It costs some preparation time to think of useful categories for the trip and sorting everything, but you will access any item in a matter of seconds without thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/travel_tips_access.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;With the bags I could easily access everything, here you can see my medication and my computer accessory bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/travel_tips_bags.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;There's even a bag for more bags. Just in case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;be-ready-for-exploring&quot;&gt;Be ready for exploring&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously you don’t want to carry around a giant backpack all the time, therefore just bring a smaller daypack with you. Make sure that it will neatly fit in your backpack, just like the sweet Russian Matryoshka dolls. If I board a plane I will keep the daypack separately with some items like laptop and e-reader. If I know I’ll have to transfer a lot, for example a bus ride and a connecting train afterwards, I’ll put everything inside the big backpack to ensure that I’ll only have to worry about one bag and I’ll have both hands free anytime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/travel_tips_daypack.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;I proudly present: Bagpackception&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;backpack-protection&quot;&gt;Backpack protection&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For backpacks that you want to check-in just buy a backpack protection. A very simple one from Tatonka I can recommend is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.de/dp/B000FSEWJC&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. It’s very cheap, just eight Euros, and effective. This simple plastic bag is very sturdy and kept my backpack protected on five flights without any signs of deterioration. You should keep zip ties with you because the attached rope to tie the bag isn’t sufficient at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/travel_tips_bag1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;At the airport it takes no more than two minutes to put your backpack inside the cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/travel_tips_bag2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;And correctly ziptied at the top even this very cheap protection cover does it's job well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;boarding-like-a-pro&quot;&gt;Boarding like a pro&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally I usually try to avoid long waiting times at the airport. That’s why I arrive at the gate later than most passengers. From this I realized that if you board the plane as last passenger you can just choose among all free seats. Now on long flights I’ll always be the last person boarding. If you’re lucky you’ll get the empty seat row you wouldn’t have gotten otherwise. So board the plane as the last person and choose where you sit freely. Sure you can’t just sit in business class, just because there’s a free seat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: Use your brains before making your life harder than necessary. Unlike at home whilst travelling there aren’t as many established structures you can rely on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marcus Ding</name></author><category term="travel" /><category term="travel" /><summary type="html">I love travelling, every now and then I have the privilege to be able to travel abroad for a longer period. In my case that usually has been about a month. And things go horribly wrong. On the one hand it means I learn something on the other hand it means things like burning 700 Euros for no other reason than being utterly stupid. Therefore I compiled this compact post about how to do things right from the beginning. Do you even prepare bro? Preparing a trip is something I’d rather avoid doing, it’s just not any fun. I once was asked by a guy on the street if he could crash my couch. As it turned out he was travelling without anything. No money, no plan, not even a backpack. He was basically homeless, just with a drive to explore the world, which made all the difference. All he had was his T-shirt, pants, shoes and most importantly: His willingness to leave his comfort zone.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digital RGB LED guide</title><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2018/08/07/digital-rgb-led-guide.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital RGB LED guide" /><published>2018-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2018/08/07/digital-rgb-led-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2018/08/07/digital-rgb-led-guide.html">&lt;p&gt;I need LEDs, a lot of LEDs. About 13.000 for a lighting project. That should be about 1400$ worth of LED. Therefore here is the result of the research I did to prevent wasting a huge load of cash I do not have anyways.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ws2801&quot;&gt;WS2801&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ws2801.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 220px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first generation of control ICs by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.world-semi.com&quot;&gt;World Semiconductor&lt;/a&gt; which requires a separate clock input additional to data (SPI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ws2811&quot;&gt;WS2811&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ws2811.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 220px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the generation after the WS2801. This IC only requires data input and works with a fixed clock speed of either 400kHz or 800kHz, which might require you to save all stripe color values in a buffer in order to match the required speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ws2812&quot;&gt;WS2812&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ws2812.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 220px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the name for an SMD LED package with an integrated WS2811 IC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ws2812b&quot;&gt;WS2812B&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ws2812b.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 220px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the improved version of the WS2812. It has a brighter LED with a more uniform color distribution. Also it features an reverse protection circuit, which will prevent breaking the stripe when attaching the power source in the wrong order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ws2813&quot;&gt;WS2813&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ws2813.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;width: 220px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the latest version. It works just like WS2812B, but also tolerates failing pixels: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a6s2MlZHnC8&quot;&gt;see video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://playground.boxtec.ch/doku.php/led/ledpixel_guide&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sk6812&quot;&gt;SK6812&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SK6812 is a clone of the WS2812, that is completely compatible. It’s PWM frequency is twice that of the WS2812B which should result in less flickering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cpldcpu.wordpress.com/2016/03/09/the-sk6812-another-intelligent-rgb-led/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apa102&quot;&gt;APA102&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These LEDs are designed by &lt;a href=&quot;http://neon-world.com/en/&quot;&gt;APA Electronic co. LTD&lt;/a&gt;. They don’t show any visible PWM flicker when moving the LED due to a very high modulation frequency (19.2 kHz). The full brighness setting (31) should be used to reduce flicker. It was tested running with 60MHz SPI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cpldcpu.wordpress.com/2014/08/27/apa102/&quot;&gt;source 1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pjrc.com/why-apa102-leds-have-trouble-at-24-mhz/&quot;&gt;source 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sk9822&quot;&gt;SK9822&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a clone of the APA102. Unfortunately it has a slightly different behaviour regarding it’s protocol since every frame will be displayed on receiving the next start frame. That results in updating all LEDs at once unlike with the APA102 or WS28XX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cpldcpu.wordpress.com/2016/12/13/sk9822-a-clone-of-the-apa102/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TO DO: write a conclusion and order LED stripe&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;SK9822&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;SK6812&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;APA102&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;WS2813&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;WS2812B&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;WS2812&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;WS2811&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;WS2801&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Update&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Simultaneous&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Staggered&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Staggered&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Staggered&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Staggered&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Staggered&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Staggered&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Staggered&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Update trigger&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Reset frame (0x00000000)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RGB data transmission&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RGB data transmission&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RGB data transmission&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RGB data transmission&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RGB data transmission&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RGB data transmission&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RGB data transmission&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;PWM Frequency&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;~4.7 kHz&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;~1.1kHz&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;~19.2 kHz&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2kHz&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;430 Hz&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;430 Hz&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;430 Hz&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.5 kHz&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Global brightness control&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;programmable current source&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;PWM at ~440 Hz&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;max data rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;30MHZ&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;800 kB/s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20MBit/s (max input clock)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;800 kB/s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;800 kB/s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;800 kB/s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;800 kB/s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;25MBit/s (max input clock)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Best Price $/m (IP30)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://de.aliexpress.com/item/5mX-New-arrival-SK9822-5050SMD-RGB-digital-flexible-led-strip-light-DC5V-input-30-32-48/32713951190.html&quot;&gt;21.42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aliexpress.com/store/product/SK6812-RGBW-similar-ws2812b-4-in-1-1m-4m-5m-30-60-144-leds-pixels-m/836457_32821691618.html&quot;&gt;16.70&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aliexpress.com/store/product/APA102-strip-1m-3m-5m-30-60-72-96-144-leds-pixels-m-APA102-Smart-led/330721_32878004298.html&quot;&gt;20.71&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://de.aliexpress.com/item/Neue-1-mt-5-mt-WS2813-Smart-led-pixel-streifen-Schwarz-Wei-PCB-30-60-leds/32864264738.html&quot;&gt;18.72&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aliexpress.com/item/individually-addressable-full-color-1-3-4-5m-waterproof-ip65-ip67-5050-rgb-30-60-144/32820264632.html&quot;&gt;13.57&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aliexpress.com/store/product/1m-4m-5m-WS2812B-Smart-led-pixel-strip-Black-White-PCB-30-60-144-leds-m/2880007_32793949673.html&quot;&gt;11.72&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;144 LED/m not possible&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;144 LED/m not possible&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;voltage-drop&quot;&gt;Voltage drop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to overcome voltage drop with long LEDs strips a higher voltage is better. Otherwise power injection every couple meters will be required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-1&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I decided to purchase the WS2812, because when ordering a lot of LEDs the price difference is very noticeable. (1680€ vs. 1050€) The data speed of 800 kBit/s is enough to run 4 meters of stripe with 60 frames per second. To me the missing features of reverse polarity protection and tolerating failing pixels isn’t worth almost twice the price if you compare WS2812 to WS2813. Also the lower PWM frequency is acceptable since the object and the viewer won’t move around very fast. Also the external resistor next to every LED is a downside compared to WS2813. 🦄🔥&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marcus Ding</name></author><category term="tech" /><category term="led" /><category term="lighting" /><summary type="html">I need LEDs, a lot of LEDs. About 13.000 for a lighting project. That should be about 1400$ worth of LED. Therefore here is the result of the research I did to prevent wasting a huge load of cash I do not have anyways.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Automating LaTeX compilation in Gitlab-CI</title><link href="https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2018/03/19/latex-in-gitlab-ci.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automating LaTeX compilation in Gitlab-CI" /><published>2018-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2018/03/19/latex-in-gitlab-ci</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kryptokommun.ist/tech/2018/03/19/latex-in-gitlab-ci.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are pushing LateX documents into a repository with all of your friends. Your friends compile the PDF files locally and sometimes push garbage into the repo. Also you want to email your assignments to your tutors. But you are already annoyed by writing commit messages. Opening your email client and dragging and dropping that PDF, for you it’s pain in it’s purest form. This makes you very sad. You ask yourself: What could I do about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combining some Python scripting and GitLab-CI configs results in a nice pipeline that processes LaTeX documents automatically while enforcing a certain folder structure. No more garbage and no more pain. Find the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline&quot;&gt;example repo here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;caption align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The working &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/pipelines&quot;&gt;GitLab CI pipeline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gitlab-ci.png&quot; alt=&quot;GitLab CI pipeline&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;caption align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The script output&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gitlab-ci-out.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;caption align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The uploaded resulting artifacts &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/-/jobs/57720189/artifacts/browse&quot;&gt;accessible in GitLab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gitlab-ci-artifacts.png&quot; alt=&quot;accessible in GitLab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;email&quot;&gt;Email&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For emailing a document for example to your tutors the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/blob/master/scripts/pipeline/latexpipeline.py&quot;&gt;scripts/pipeline/latexpipeline.py&lt;/a&gt; submodule will parse the commit message and search for the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--final&lt;/code&gt; flag. In our example the commit message&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Add my assignment no 5 --final assignment_papers/documentfoldername --comment Sorry for my late submission, it will not happen again! 😇💋
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;would result in an raw text email being sent to the recipient specified in &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/blob/master/scripts/pipeline_script.py&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scripts/pipeline_script.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with the email of the GitLab User being CCed as Reply-To.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;caption align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The mail being sent to the address defined in &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/blob/master/scripts/pipeline_script.py&quot;&gt;scripts/pipeline_script.py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gitlab-ci-mail.png&quot; alt=&quot;scripts/pipeline_script.py&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;telegram-and-iftt&quot;&gt;Telegram and IFTT&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a little help by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ifttt.com&quot;&gt;IFTTT.com&lt;/a&gt; it’s very easy to integrate Telegram notifications into the system using a bot. One benefit is certainly shaming users into testing their TeX files before submitting them knowing that their utter failure will be public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;caption align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Exemplary Telegram notifications about successes and failures&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gitlab-ci-telegram.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;caption align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;The applets for the bachelorprojects Telegram group including the Webhook based applet forwarding messages to the Telegram bot.&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gitlab-ci-ifttt.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-short-intro-to-gitlab-ci&quot;&gt;A short intro to GitLab CI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gitlab.com/ce/ci/README.html&quot;&gt;GitLab CI&lt;/a&gt; is like any other continuous integration platform with the additional feature of &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/project/pipelines/job_artifacts.html&quot;&gt;job artifacts&lt;/a&gt;. This means a job can produce files as output that will be stored and and can be directly linked to on the GitLab platform. Of course this is ideal for our LaTeX pipeline. Let’s take a look at the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;compile_pdf&lt;/code&gt; stage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-yml&quot; data-lang=&quot;yml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;compile_pdf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;stage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;compile_pdf&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;before_script&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;rm -rf htmlcov&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;script&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;python3 scripts/pipeline_script.py run &quot;$GITLAB_USER_NAME&quot; $CI_JOB_ID &quot;$(git log -1 --pretty=%B)&quot; $GITLAB_USER_EMAIL $CI_PROJECT_URL&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;cache&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;single_pdfs&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;paths&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;assignment_papers/latex_output&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;letters/latex_output&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;artifacts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;paths&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;assignment_papers/*.pdf&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;letters/*.pdf&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;only&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;master&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First it executes the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/blob/master/scripts/pipeline_script.py&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scripts/pipeline_script.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; script. The necessary arguments are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gitlab.com/ce/ci/variables/README.html&quot;&gt;GitLab variables&lt;/a&gt; &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$GITLAB_USER_NAME&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$CI_JOB_ID&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$GITLAB_USER_EMAIL&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$CI_PROJECT_URL&lt;/code&gt; as well as the current commit message: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$(git log -1 --pretty=%B)&lt;/code&gt;. The executed &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/blob/master/scripts/pipeline_script.py&quot;&gt;scripts/pipeline_script.py&lt;/a&gt; will write all files resulting from document compilation to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;assignment_papers/latex_output/*&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;letters/latex_output/*&lt;/code&gt; and copy the PDFs to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;assignment_papers/*.pdf&lt;/code&gt; and `letters/*.pdf/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting the key &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cache&lt;/code&gt; results in all files specified under &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;paths&lt;/code&gt; being cached between job runs given you’re using a dedicated &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gitlab.com/ce/ci/runners/README.html&quot;&gt;GitLab runner&lt;/a&gt;. Alos it will speed up compilation because documents will only be recompiled if there’s a change. In our example case it reduced the runtime from 5 minutes to just 1 minute. Unfortunately the free shared runners on gitlab.com don’t allow this. But what about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/project/pipelines/job_artifacts.html&quot;&gt;job artifacts&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/blob/master/scripts/pipeline_script.py&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scripts/pipeline_script.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; script will copy the resulting PDFs from &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;foldername/latex_output/*pdf&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;foldername/*.pdf&lt;/code&gt;. This happens at the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PIPELINE.move_pdfs()&lt;/code&gt; function call. Thus we specify under &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;artifacts&lt;/code&gt; the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;paths&lt;/code&gt; where GitLab CI will look for matching files to store them as artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;image-table&quot;&gt;
&lt;caption align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Processing time without caching and with enabled caching.&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gitlab-ci-caching.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-does-the-script-do&quot;&gt;What does the script do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately after checking that the folder structures are compliant the script will execute the following lines in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/blob/master/scripts/pipeline/latexpipeline.py&quot;&gt;scripts/pipeline/latexpipeline.py&lt;/a&gt; submodule:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dir_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;second_level_items&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;items&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;main_filename&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dir_name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;.tex&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;folderpath&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;join&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;relative_path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dir_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'cd &quot;{fp}&quot; &amp;amp;&amp;amp; latexmk -output-directory=../latex_output -pdf &quot;{f}&quot;'&lt;/span&gt;\
                &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot; -e '$pdflatex=q/pdflatex &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;O -shell-escape &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;S/'&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;\
                &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;folderpath&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;main_filename&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;call&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sccmsg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\033&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;[92mCompiled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\033&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;[94m{d}.tex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\033&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;[92m successfully&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\033&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;[0m&quot;&lt;/span&gt;\
                    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dir_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sccmsg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;errmsg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\033&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;[91mError with compiling &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\033&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;[94m{d}.tex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\033&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;[0m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;cmd: {c}&quot;&lt;/span&gt;\
                    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dir_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;error_notify_and_exit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;errmsg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dictionary &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;second_level_items&lt;/code&gt; contains all but the exempted subfolders in a valid root subdirectory. Now all it does for a folder called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;documentfoldername&lt;/code&gt; residing in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;assignment_papers&lt;/code&gt; is executing these commands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot; data-lang=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;documentfoldername
latexmk &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-output-directory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;../latex_output &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-pdf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;documentfoldername.tex&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'$pdflatex=q/pdflatex %O -shell-escape %S/'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After executing the script will print a success message. If the command fails it will notify about this and exit with an error so that the GitLab job will fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enforcing-folder-rules&quot;&gt;Enforcing folder rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/blob/master/scripts/pipeline_script.py&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scripts/pipeline_script.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; enforces a folder structure like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;.
|
+--assignment_papers
|  +--documentfoldername
|  |  +--figures
|  |  |  +--example.png
|  |  +--documentfoldername.tex
|  |  +--preamble.tex
|  |  +--content.tex
|  +--otherdocumentfoldername
|  |  +--figures
|  |  |  +--example.pdf
|  |  +--otherdocumentfoldername.tex
|  |  +--preamble.tex
|  |  +--content.tex
+--letters
|  +--documentfoldername
|  |  +--figures
|  |  |  +--example.jpg
|  |  +--documentfoldername.tex
|  +--otherdocumentfoldername
|  |  +--figures
|  |  |  +--example.jpg
|  |  +--otherdocumentfoldername.tex
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there can be multiple folders the root directory
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;assignment_papers&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;subfolders must contain &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; files with the same name&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;subfolders must contain &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;preamble.tex&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;subfolders must contain &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;content.tex&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;subfolders may contain a figures folder&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;letters&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;subfolders must contain &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; files with the same name&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;subfolders may contain a figures folder&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These rules are determined in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/blob/master/scripts/pipeline_script.py&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scripts/pipeline_script.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURES&lt;/code&gt; dictionary. It maps the root level subfolder names to folder structure rules formatted as dictionaries. For example if a subfolders name begins with a string in the list referenced by the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;exempt_dirs_start_with&quot;&lt;/code&gt; key it will be exempted from being processed by the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#root level directories we won't process&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;EXEMPT_DIRS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;scripts&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;__pycache__&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#dirs starting with given string in LateXPipeline.relative_path will be ignored&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#also applied to root level dirs&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;EXEMPT_DIRS_START_WITH&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#files mandatory in each LaTeX folder&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;MANDATORY_FILES_ASSIGNMENT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;preamble.tex&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;references.bib&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;content.tex&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#directories in LateXPipeline.relative_path the pipeline will ignore&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;EXEMPT_DIRS_ASSIGNMENT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;latex_output&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;BP_COMBINED&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;__pycache__&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#folders allowed but not mandatory in subdirectories&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ALLOWED_SUBDIRS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;figures&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#allowed folder structure for folder assignment_papers&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURE_ASSIGNMENT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;exempt_dirs&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;EXEMPT_DIRS_ASSIGNMENT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;\
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;exempt_dirs_start_with&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;EXEMPT_DIRS_START_WITH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;\
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;mandatory_files&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;MANDATORY_FILES_ASSIGNMENT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;\
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;allowed_subdirs&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ALLOWED_SUBDIRS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#allowed folder structure for folder letters&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURE_LETTERS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURE_ASSIGNMENT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURE_LETTERS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;mandatory_files&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#different folder structures for each root level dir&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#test_root_folder(_one/two) is necessary for pytest testing&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURES&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;test_root_folder&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURE_ASSIGNMENT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;\
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;test_script_root_folder&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURE_ASSIGNMENT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;\
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;test_folder_one&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURE_ASSIGNMENT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;test_folder_two&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURE_ASSIGNMENT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;\
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;assignment_papers&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURE_ASSIGNMENT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;letters&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FOLDER_STRUCTURE_LETTERS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;known-issues&quot;&gt;Known issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is still a problem with calculating the code coverage. As seen in the current &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline&quot;&gt;example repo &lt;/a&gt; the displayed code coverage is just about 80% when it should be very close to 100 percent. Unfortunately the tests in &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/kryptokommunist/latexpipeline/blob/master/scripts/tests/test_latexpipeline.py&quot;&gt;scripts/tests/test_latexpipeline.py&lt;/a&gt; calling the script with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;subprocess.run&lt;/code&gt; won’t be measured by &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;codecov&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;test_console_test_usage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;Check that Latexmk actually works and the module can be invoked as script from command line&quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ret&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;subprocess&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;python3 &quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;RELATIVE_SCRIPT_PATH&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;' test test@test.de &quot;Test --meta lol&quot;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;\
         &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;SCRIPT_TEST_ROOT_DIR_PATH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;stderr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;subprocess&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PIPE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;stdout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;subprocess&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PIPE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ret&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;stderr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;assert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;YAY&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ret&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;stdout&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;assert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Latexmk&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ret&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;stderr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Marcus Ding</name></author><category term="tech" /><category term="gitlab-ci" /><category term="latex" /><category term="python" /><summary type="html">The problem You are pushing LateX documents into a repository with all of your friends. Your friends compile the PDF files locally and sometimes push garbage into the repo. Also you want to email your assignments to your tutors. But you are already annoyed by writing commit messages. Opening your email client and dragging and dropping that PDF, for you it’s pain in it’s purest form. This makes you very sad. You ask yourself: What could I do about it?</summary></entry></feed>